<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The late proposal of union among Protestants, review'd and rectifi'd being a vindication of the most reverend father in God, Edwin, Lord Arch-Bishop of York, and the reverend Dr. Tillotson, Dean of Canterbury, from the misprisions of an apocryphal proposer : with a full answer to his proposal, presented to the Parliament.</title>
            <author>Womock, Laurence, 1612-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66898</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3345</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20318</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12733949</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12733949</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66526</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66898)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66526)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 994:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The late proposal of union among Protestants, review'd and rectifi'd being a vindication of the most reverend father in God, Edwin, Lord Arch-Bishop of York, and the reverend Dr. Tillotson, Dean of Canterbury, from the misprisions of an apocryphal proposer : with a full answer to his proposal, presented to the Parliament.</title>
                  <author>Womock, Laurence, 1612-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. Godbid and J. Playford, for R. Clavel ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>NUC attributes this work to Laurence Womock.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sandys, Edwin, 1516?-1588.</term>
               <term>Tillotson, John, 1630-1694.</term>
               <term>Protestantism --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66526:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LATE PROPOSAL OF UNION AMONG PROTESTANTS, Review'd and Rectifi'd:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BEING</hi> A VINDICATION of the moſt Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father in God, <hi>EDWIN,</hi> Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>York;</hi> And the Reverend Dr. <hi>Tillotſon,</hi> Dean of <hi>Canterbury;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>FROM</hi> The <hi>Miſpriſions</hi> of an Apocryphal Propoſer; With a full ANSWER to his PROPOSAL:</p>
            <p>Preſented to the PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 129. 1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Saepe oppugnaverunt à juventute, verùm non praevaluerunt.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 51.32.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>(Et) qui (adhuc) vexant, dicunt, Inclinare &amp; tranſibimus.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by <hi>A. Godbid</hi> and <hi>J. Playford,</hi> for <hi>R. Clavel,</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:66526:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:66526:2"/>
            <head>THE LATE PROPOSAL OF UNION AMONGST PROTESTANTS Preſented to the PARLIAMENT, <hi>Review'd and Rectifi'd.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Received your Letter, and I have ſeriouſly peruſed the Addreſs, Humbly preſented to the <hi>Parliament;</hi> I like the Title very well, [<hi>A Propoſal of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion amongſt Proteſtants</hi>] and the Deſign, in general, cannot but be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended: but how well it is inforced from the <hi>laſt Will</hi> of the moſt Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Dr.<hi>Sands,</hi> ſome time a Arch-Biſhop of <hi>York;</hi> and whether that is to be lookt upon as the Sentiment of the <hi>firſt Reformers,</hi> will require a farther Examination. In the interim, as once for the Diviſions of <hi>Reuben,</hi> ſo now for thoſe of <hi>England,</hi> there are <hi>great thoughts of heart;</hi> and who knows not, that Peace is a Jewel of great price, and to be purchaſed at any rate that may reaſonably ſecure the poſſeſſion of it. This indeed is the <hi>Legacy</hi> which our deareſt Lord hath left to his Diſciples: But alas! many of the <hi>Legatees</hi> have renounced their part in it; becauſe they cannot be allowed to make their <hi>own</hi> will of his Church and Kingdom. By Peace, our Bleſſed Lord never intended a Conſpiracy againſt the Rules of Decency and Order: Peace with God, and Conſcience, and amongſt Brethren, is the Fruit of Righteouſneſs.<note n="(a)" place="margin">Iſa. 32.17.</note> Righteouſneſs is the Foundation of Chriſt's Kingdom, and Peace a Superſtructure.<note n="(b)" place="margin">Rom. 14.17.</note> Now you know 'tis the part of Righteouſneſs, to give every one their due; the beſt Method therefore to be at Peace, is to become juſt, that is, to become obedient, and to pay our due reſpects to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:66526:3"/>the <hi>Laws,</hi> and to our <hi>Superiours.</hi> The Author of <hi>one Project</hi> for the good of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> tells us, <hi>That good Laws, and a juſt Execution of them</hi> (and not Oaths) <hi>are the natural and real Security of a Government.</hi> I am very much of his mind herein: For to relax the Reins of Government, opens a door to Licentiouſneſs; and that is no good friend to Peace and Unity. Beſides, if there can be ſuch a thing as a <hi>Rope</hi> of Sand, there may be a ſtupid quietneſs betwixt the parts, but no ſolid, uſeful ſtrength; which depends upon Command and Order, as much as the attra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive ſplendour and beauty of Societies. This, <hi>Sir,</hi> is one Reaſon, why the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> ſo little value the ſhatter'd Parties of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> that they think them not worth a <hi>Conſult</hi> or <hi>Plot,</hi> in compariſon of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Let Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity be own'd as ſacred, and the Laws be kept inviolable, and theſe will prove the beſt Bulwark of our Peace and Union. Proteſtants abroad are generally of this perſuaſion; and if any of our own Communion be otherwiſe minded, we are to look upon them as looſe Stones, that will never ſtand to ſupport the Building, but rather flinch and ſlip away to betray it, as occaſion ſerves.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi> complain of hard meaſure, heavy burthens, and oppreſſing yoaks, as if their Perſons were impriſoned under hatches, their Eſtates torn from them under the Harrows of Sequeſtrators, and their Wives and Children forced to dance a tedious attendance at <hi>Goldſmiths-Hall,</hi> to make their Compoſition; whereas, in truth, it is the great advantage ſome of them reap from thence, which makes them ſtill in love with their <hi>gainful Meetings</hi> againſt Authority.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Apocryphal Anonymus</hi> tells us, theſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi> would do any thing for Peace, <hi>only they dare not forſake Holineſs, neglect their Duty, nor wound their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, by offending God. Sir,</hi> if there be not ſome foul tincture of Malice in theſe Inſinuations, yet are they no leſs unjuſt and ſcandalous, than extravagant. What Law, what Canon, what Rite, or Practice, injoin'd by the Conſtitutions of this Church; or what Governour amongſt us, does oblige them to any ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, nay that does not charge and fortifie them to do the contrary? As a learned man told thoſe <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> in the days of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> With us <hi>there is leave for all men to be good, if they will by God's grace endeavour it.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Laur. Deios.</hi> That the Pope is that Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, <hi>pa.</hi> 147. <hi>Printed</hi> 1590. <hi>and Preached at St.</hi> Paul<hi>'s-Croſs.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe <hi>deſperate Plots,</hi> that are on foot againſt this poor maligned Church, we reſent with no leſs horror than themſelves: But while the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Emiſſaries,</hi> the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> with their <hi>Vaſſals,</hi> are at work to undermine the Foundation, Why do theſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi> make it their buſineſs to aſſault and batter the Walls and Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets of it? They attempt to blow it up, and theſe ſeek to pull it down: they endeavour to extinguiſh the Name and Eſſence; and at the ſame time (as co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>operating to her ruin) theſe labour (at leaſt) to Eclipſe the Glory of it. The learned Author,<note place="margin">Ibid. p. <hi>178.</hi>
               </note> even now mentioned, had good ground to conclude, <hi>That if any thing will bring the</hi> Antichriſtian <hi>Yoak upon this Land again, (which God turn far from us) it will be Diſſention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We readily grant, that <hi>violent ſtorms</hi> ſhould drive the <hi>Sheep</hi> together; burin ſuch a ſeaſon, all ſober men will think, that the <hi>ſtragling ſheep</hi> ſhould run into the common <hi>Fold,</hi> and not quarrel with their faithful Shepherd; nor labour to pluck down that Fold which is their beſt ſhelter. We know too, without this <hi>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>leſs</hi> Informer, That the <hi>Red of God</hi> ſhould teach us peace and quietneſs; and having been ſo many years in the <hi>Furnace</hi> of Affliction, we ſhould be ſo throughly melted, as to run eaſily into <hi>one:</hi> But whether it be more reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able that the Church ſhould run into their <hi>Conventicles,</hi> (which can never be united) or their <hi>Conventicles</hi> into the <hi>boſom</hi> of the Church, let wiſe men judge. This Church of <hi>England</hi> has been as a <hi>Lilly amongst the Thorns;</hi> and the <hi>diſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> Party has been the <hi>Rod</hi> of God's indignation, to chaſtiſe her: but tho the Rod be not caſt into the <hi>Fire</hi> (through the clemency of a gracious Sovereign) vet ſhe like <hi>Moſes</hi> his <hi>Buſh</hi> has been miraculouſly preſerved in the midſt of flames; and the right hand of the Moſt High has been no leſs remarkable in her Enemies defeat, than in her own happy reſtauration. Nor is it unknown to the wiſely conſiderative, what <hi>Relentings</hi> ſhe has had, while they have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted <hi>ſtubborn</hi> and <hi>inflexible.</hi> Nevertheleſs this officious <hi>Advocate</hi> craves leave,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:66526:3"/>to beg on their behalf, <hi>That what God hath not ſet up in the Church may he pull'd down; and that rejected, as an Innovation, which is not as old as the Apoſtles, and and nothing impoſed upon Miniſters or People, but what hath footing and warraint in the holy Scriptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, That we have nothing eſtabliſh'd in our Church, but what God hath ſet up by <hi>general directions</hi> and a <hi>juſt authority;</hi> nor have we any thing in uſe and practice amongſt us, but what is [in the <hi>root</hi> and ground of it] as old as the Apoſtles: nor is any thing impoſed upon Miniſters or People, but what hath ſuch ſufficient footing and warrant in the Holy Scriptures. That the Church hath power to inſtitute external Rites, preſcribe Forms, to make Canons and Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to aſſiſt her Children, and regulate their Practice in the publick Worſhip and Service of God, is not onely the unanimous Confeſſion of all Proteſtant Churches of any <hi>creditable</hi> denomination; but is exactly conſonant to the mind of God, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to us in his holy Scriptures, where he gives the Church a charge to <hi>do all things to edification,</hi> and <hi>to his glory.</hi> To this end he enjoyns her to perform all her holy Offices <hi>decently and in goad order.</hi> This is God's expreſs command in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, but his Word hath no where determined the particulars, wherein that <hi>decency or order</hi> does or ſhall conſiſt; it follows therefore undeniably, that the Word of God or the Holy Scriptures do ſuppoſe or eſtabliſh a Power in the Church to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute Rules, preſcribe Forms, and make Canons to that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>For a clearer Demonſtration hereof let us ſeriouſly reflect upon theſe Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Chriſt and his Apoſtles intended Unity, and to obtain and preſerve that Unity they enjoyned Order and Uniformity in the Churches. Chriſt's intent is evident in his ardent Prayer, that his Diſciples might<note n="a" place="margin">Joh. 17.</note> 
               <hi>be one, and made perfect in one.</hi> And we may read the great Apoſtle's aim in his earneſt conjuring them,<note n="b" place="margin">Eph. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>to keep the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 16.17.</note> 
               <hi>For there is one body and one ſpirit, one Lord and one Faith, one Baptiſm, one Hope of our calling.</hi> And elſewhere he is no leſs vehement; <hi>Now I beſeech you, Brethren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.17.</note> 
               <hi>mark them which cauſe diviſions and offences, contrary to the doctrine which ye have learned, and avoid them.</hi> That <hi>Order and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> are enjoyned to preſerve this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> is no leſs evident;<note n="d" place="margin">1 Cor. 14.40</note> 
               <hi>Let all things be done decently and in order. Order</hi> is the <hi>Parent of Decency;</hi> and to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ſame <hi>Rule</hi> is to follow Order. Hence the Apoſtle exhorts the <hi>Philippians,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Phil. 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>Let us walk by the ſame rule, let us mind the ſame things.</hi> And this is the onely way to keep out Schiſm; whereupon he uſeth this Obſervation to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>Now I beſeech you, Brethren, by the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ye all ſpeak the ſame thing, and that there be no diviſions amongſt you; but that ye be perfectly joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together in the ſame mind and in the ſame judgment.</hi> And he tells us to what end he requires this, <hi>viz. That ye may with one mind and one mouth glorifie God,<note place="margin">Rom. 15.6.</note> even the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And upon this account their <hi>Order</hi> in the Church of <hi>Coloſs</hi> was a Proſpect of ſo much pleaſure to him:<note place="margin">Col. 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>For though I am abſent in the fleſh, yet am I with you in the ſpirit, joying and beholding your order, and the ſtedfaſtneſs of your faith in Chriſt.</hi> For when men begin to break order, they preſently grow <hi>looſe</hi> in their Faith both to God and Man.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider, that the Apoſtles, at their firſt Preaching of the Goſpel, did not preſently eſtabliſh that Order, which the ſtate of the Church did afterward require. The Church was to be gathered firſt, and afterwards Orders preſcribed how it ſhould be governed. This is evident not onely from thoſe <hi>Decrees</hi> made in the firſt Council at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but from the expreſs reſolution of S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 15. 1 Cor. 11.34.</note> 
               <hi>the reſt will I ſet in order when I come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider, that the Apoſtle expected ſuch a Settlement ſhould be made by ſuch as were intruſted with the Government of the Church. This is clear from his advice and command to <hi>Titus, For this cauſe left I thee in Crete, that thou ſhouldeſt ſet in order the things that are wanting,</hi> or left undone. From whence two things may be inferr'd irrefragably; 1. That at his <hi>firſt</hi> Preaching of the Goſpel S. <hi>Paul</hi> left ſome things undone, which in his own judgment were afterwards fit to be done. 2. That he expected the performance thereof from the care of <hi>Titus.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:66526:4"/>
            <p n="4">4. Conſider, that the Apoſtle gives certain <hi>general rules</hi> or Canons to direct the Governours of the Church,<note place="margin">Inſtit. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>19.</hi> ſect. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> in making ſuch Eſtabliſhments: ſuch are theſe, <hi>Let all things be done to the glory of God. Let all things be done to edification. Let all things be done decently and in order.</hi> Hereupon Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> does acknowledge ſuch Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Conſtitutions to be <hi>lawful,</hi> as <hi>conſonant to the Word of God.</hi> And <hi>Beza</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts them <hi>celeſtial and divine,</hi> in reſpect of their <hi>foundation and end,</hi> which is that general <hi>decorum</hi> commanded to be obſerved in God's Worſhip.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Conſider, that the Apoſtle left it to the Judgment of Church-Governours to determine the <hi>particulars</hi> to be eſtabliſhed in ſuch caſes. <hi>For this cauſe left I thee</hi> (<hi>Titus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Titus 1.5.</note> a ſingle perſon, and at leaſt a Biſhop) <hi>in Crete, that thou ſhouldeſt ſet in order the things that are wanting. David, Solomon,</hi> and <hi>Jehoſaphat, Hezekiah, Joſiah,</hi> and all godly Princes, made Laws for the Church of God, and were approved: yea, the Laws and Decrees of <hi>Nebuchadnezar,</hi> of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and <hi>Darius,</hi> were for the benefit of it. And God hath promiſed, that <hi>Kings ſhall be nurſing fathers, and Queens nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing mothers, to the Church.</hi> And it was truly and worthily ſaid in Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths</hi> time, by that Author before mentioned, <hi>That Princes eſpecially ſerve Chriſt even in making Laws for Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">L. Drios p. <hi>162</hi>
               </note> Now let us lay theſe Principles together: 1 That the ſolemn Worſhip and Service of God cannot be performed without <hi>Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> (for of neceſſity Circumſtances muſt cloath every action under the Sun.) 2. That theſe <hi>Circumſtances</hi> are to be obſerved according to the rules of <hi>decency and order;</hi> and that <hi>theſe</hi> rules are to be <hi>adjudged and determined</hi> by ſuch as are inveſted with <hi>Authority</hi> to that effect; it will follow unavoidably, that all Subjects and Members of the Church are obliged in Conſcience to obey ſuch Determinations and Eſtabliſhments. For 'tis moſt certain, where ſome are impowered to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, others are enjoyned to obey; elſe the Power given to Superiours were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to no effect.<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi ſupra.</note> Hereupon Mr. <hi>Beza</hi> does acknowledge, though theſe Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Conſtitutions be <hi>humane and mutable,</hi> and do not bind the Conſcience <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly and of themſelves;</hi> yet if they be <hi>juſt and honeſt,</hi> we are obliged to obſerve them, <hi>as they contribute to the edification of the Church,</hi> and that we may <hi>avoid ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal.</hi> Nor want we a better Authority than that of Mr. <hi>Beza,</hi> the great Apoſtle gives this charge,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.17.</note> 
               <hi>Obey them that have the rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves.</hi> If you demand how far this Submiſſion does extend, the Apoſtle has reſolved that too to a reaſonable ſatisfaction, <hi>Whatſoever things are true, whatſoever things are honeſt,</hi> [ſuch as are venerable for their gravity and comlineſs] <hi>whatſoever things are juſt,<note place="margin">Georg. Calixt.</note> whatſoever things are pure, whatſoever things are lovely, whatſoever things are of good report; if there be any virtue, and if there be any praiſe, think on theſe things to do them.</hi> I am very confident there is nothing enjoyned in this Church of <hi>England,</hi> but what is very fairly comprehended within this Latitude of the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>But this Author goes on with confidence, and tells his Reader, that <hi>certainly it cannot be prejudicial to the Church, to yield in thoſe things which ſhe her ſelf calls indiffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent; and upon that ſcore are at beſt</hi> (according to his Irreverence) <hi>but Chips in Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridge, not worth contending for.</hi> But in all matters of <hi>indifferency</hi> we ſay theſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi> have the ſame liberty to <hi>comply</hi> with, as we have to <hi>recede</hi> from the uſe and practice of them. And herein we judge it moſt convenient and dutiful, both for our ſelves and them, to conform to the Law and Judgment of our Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours. The Apoſtle was ſometime very <hi>tender</hi> and yielding in matters of <hi>indiffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency</hi> to the <hi>infirmity</hi> of new Converts; but it was in favour of ſuch as had been prepoſſeſs'd by <hi>education and the appearance of a divine Law,</hi> and but <hi>lately</hi> call'd off from the prejudice of ſuch a Diſpenſation; and this was <hi>before</hi> ſuch time as Authority had thought fit to <hi>determine</hi> any thing in the caſe. But this is not pleadable in Bar to a <hi>deliberate</hi> and legal Settlement of <hi>Rites and Orders</hi> for the Diſcipline and Practice of the Church in after Ages. And I pray remember, it was a thing <hi>indifferent,</hi> which God himſelf was pleas'd to make choice of for the <hi>tryal</hi> and exerciſe of Man's Obedience. The Law of Nature did not tie up the hands of our <hi>firſt</hi> Parents from the <hi>Tree of Knowledge;</hi> it was but a <hi>poſitive</hi> Law, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trench'd their Liberty from the uſe and pleaſure of it. And I am afraid it is that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:66526:4"/>
               <hi>forbidden fruit</hi> which hath <hi>ſet mens teeth on edge,</hi> and makes them at this day ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apt to reliſh any <hi>reſtraint</hi> in matters of Indifferency. For (to let us ſee the great Veneration they have for Authority when it is not <hi>veſted in themſelves</hi>) they ſtick not to tell us plainly, that what they have <hi>a moral liberty</hi> to do, they will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore refuſe and contradict, becauſe <hi>commanded</hi> by Authority. But if we duly weight how <hi>fatal</hi> the Tranſgreſſion was in the firſt Inſtance of that nature, me thinks it ſhould make us dread the Iſſue; leſt (beſides what we have contracted from <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin) we ſhould draw a further Guilt upon our ſelves, by an untoward and unwarrantable <hi>imitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this <hi>Pius Anonymus</hi> is very much miſtaken in affirming, it cannot be <hi>prejudicial</hi> to the Church, to yield to thoſe things which <hi>ſhe herſelf calls indifferent,</hi> ſeeing theſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi> account them <hi>ſinful;</hi> for herein they willingly renounce their own <hi>liberty,</hi> that they may <hi>prejudge</hi> ours; and by this means they become uncharitable to us, and <hi>dogmatize</hi> themſelves into that very <hi>Superſtition</hi> which the Apoſtle condemns amongſt the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> [<hi>Touch not, taste not, handle not.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 2.2.</note>] That this ſqueamiſh refuſal of things indifferent is <hi>Superſtition,</hi> we have good warrant from the nature<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Plut. de ſuperſtitione.</note> of the thing, as well as from the words of the Apoſtle; for what is <hi>Superſtition</hi> but <hi>a vain and anxious obſervation</hi> of things above the<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>common rule</hi> and ſtandard <hi>as matters of Religion.</hi> A ſuperſtitious man is a perſon affected with a vain and ſuperfluous fear of God; <hi>Qui metuit ibi Deum offendere, ubi non offenditur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Calvin;</hi> One that fears to offend God in that wherein he is not offended.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Lexicon Jurid. verbo ſuperſtitioſus.</note> And this may conſiſt in <hi>Abſtention and Omiſſion,</hi> as well as in any <hi>Addition</hi> whatſoever.<note n="c" place="margin">Si quis contra mandatum Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini in ſolo pane celebraret, eſſet ſurperſtitio; eſt enim haec priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio ſuperſlua. Et licet omiſſio minas ponat in re quam eſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat, animus tamen ſic omittendi, plus ponit in voluntate, quam per legem Religionis eſſe debeat. <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derus de Juſt. &amp; Relig. Tract. 10. c. 7. dub. 1. ad. 4.</hi>
               </note> For <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition</hi> is a <hi>ſcrupulous excreſcence of fear,</hi> which grows reſpectively out of <hi>both ſides</hi> of Religion; if you pleaſe you may call it <hi>poſitive</hi> or <hi>negative.</hi> The <hi>poſitive Superſtition</hi> conſiſts in a <hi>ſcrupulous obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> or the doing of ſomething which God hath not commanded, or (if once he had) has now aboliſhed. Of this kind of Superſtition mention is made by the Apoſtle in divers places, and particularly <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.10, 11. <hi>Ye obſerve, days, and moneths, and times, and years: I am afraid of you leſt I have beſtowed upon you labour in vain.</hi> The Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of<note n="d" place="margin">Erat enim legalis Obſervantia jam olim pro tempore Religio, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inde facta eſt Superſtitio. <hi>Ambr. Cathar. ad Col. 2.18.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Times, Rites, and Ceremonies,</hi> matters of Indifferency in their own nature, when obtruded upon us as part of God's Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as matters of Religion and Merit, as neceſſary to Salvation, as Duties of Holineſs and Righteouſneſs, as obligatory to Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of their own nature, <hi>this</hi> is determined to be Superſtition. But when they are enjoyned to prevent<note n="e" place="margin">See the 20th. of the Queen's Injunctions.</note> 
               <hi>diſorder,</hi> and keep up a <hi>ſolemn gravity and decorum,</hi> in the Performance of all Sacred Offices in God's Publick Worſhip and Service; <hi>in this caſe</hi> they are no way <hi>allied</hi> to Superſtition, but depend upon the lawful Power and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of ſuch as are intruſted with the Conduct of the Church. This is the unanimous Acknowledgment of the moſt Learned Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, <hi>Calvin, Aretius, Zanchy, Davenant,</hi> as may be obſerved in their reſpective <hi>Commentaries</hi> upon <hi>Col.</hi> 2.16. <hi>&amp; Gal.</hi> 4.10. to which I refer the Judicious Reader.</p>
            <p>There is a <hi>ſecond</hi> kind of <hi>Superſtition,</hi> which we may call<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Plut. de ſuperſtit.</note> 
               <hi>Negative,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in a <hi>vain</hi> and <hi>ſcrupulous Omiſſion, Averſation, and Abſtinence</hi> from ſuch things as God hath no where forbidden. Thus the Reverend Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> concerning <hi>Sunday (Dies Solis)</hi> that ſome men are ſhy of the Name, and condemn the uſe of it as <hi>profane, heatheniſh, and unlawful,</hi> it proceeds (he ſaith) from<note n="g" place="margin">In the firſt of his 8 Caſes.</note> 
               <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition.</hi> But we have the Apoſtle's Inſtance, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.20. <hi>If you be dead with Chriſt from the rudiments of the world, why as though living in the world are ye ſubject to ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,</hi> (and what are they but<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ne eſitave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.</hi> G. Calixt.</note> Prohibitions and Negatives?) <hi>Touch not, taſte not, handle not?</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Grot. ad Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſ. 2.16.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nâ clauſulâ comprehendit &amp; Judaizantes &amp; Pythagorizantes, vino abſtinere perpetud non erat Judaicum, niſi in paucis: apud Pythagoriſtas frequens. Cibis nonnullis Judaei abſtinebant, multo pluribus Pythagoriſtae. —Ne admitte tales magiſtros, qui talia non obſervantes ſpeſalutis excludunt. <hi>Haec Grotius.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>De creſcentibus verbis indicatur in quantum creverit ſuperſtitio,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:66526:5"/>ſaith <hi>Calixtus; The leſſening of the words does intimate the increaſe of Superſtition.</hi> And he does make uſe of the Number <hi>Three</hi> that he may comprehend all, ſaith <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jetan.</hi> And (as he goes on) though we cannot tell certainly and <hi>in ſpecie, what Ordinances</hi> he means, yet we are ſure they concern <hi>Obſervances of an external car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal nature</hi> as <hi>Religious.</hi> But by the <hi>Cardinal</hi>'s good leave they placed <hi>Religion</hi> in the <hi>Averſation and Non-obſervance</hi> of them; wherein the Apoſtle reproves their <hi>vain Scrupuloſity and affected Superſtition.</hi> Modern Expoſitors have not expreſs'd themſelves diſtinctly and clearly in this matter:<note place="margin">Ad Col. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> but S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> (though in few words) delivers himſelf full enough to our purpoſe; <hi>Omnis qui baptizatur in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto moritur mundo: cunctis enim ſuperſtitionum erroribus abrenunciat, &amp; ſolam colit fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Chriſti. Every one that is baptized into Chriſt is dead to the world: for he renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth all the errors of Superſtition, that he may obſerve the faith of Chriſt onely as his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi> Thoſe <hi>beggarly Elements</hi> of the <hi>Levitical</hi> Law, and the <hi>Traditions and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances</hi> of old <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> calls the Obſervance of them <hi>Superſtition.</hi> For <hi>Superſtition</hi> is an awful <hi>veneration</hi> of ſomething that is <hi>dead</hi> under a notion that it ſtill <hi>lives</hi> in a ſtate of Glory. Now thoſe <hi>Philoſophical and Jewiſh</hi> Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (which the Apoſtle reproves) are as well dead to <hi>us</hi> as we to <hi>them.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore look upon them as <hi>ſurviving</hi> thoſe Diſpenſations which gave them life and <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and to have their <hi>imaginary</hi> Ghoſts in <hi>veneration,</hi> is certainly a moſt vain and groſs Superſtition. To ſhut up this part of our Diſcourſe: By things <hi>indifferent</hi> we mean ſuch things as God hath left <hi>free</hi> to us;<note place="margin">Col. 2.16.</note> things neither <hi>commanded nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden,</hi> concerning which theſe Rules may be of uſe to direct our common Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Such as are afraid they ſhould offend God and wound their Conſcience,<note place="margin">Col. 2.21. 1 Cor. 10.25, 27.</note> by the <hi>uſe and practice</hi> of ſuch things as God hath not forbidden, <hi>they</hi> are ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Such as are afraid they ſhould offend God and wound their Conſciences,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.10, 11. Mar. 7.5, &amp;c.</note> by the <hi>omiſſion or diſuſe</hi> of ſuch things as God hath not commanded, they are Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Such as make the <hi>uſe and practice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Such was the Caſe in Gal. 4.10, 11. &amp; Mar. 7.5.</note> or the <hi>omiſſion and forbearance,</hi> of things <hi>indifferent,</hi> a matter of <hi>merit of Religion or Divine Worſhip,</hi> of <hi>neceſſity</hi> to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Juſtification, and Holineſs, and <hi>binding</hi> the Conſcience of their <hi>own nature,</hi> or upon any ſuch account, <hi>they</hi> are Superſtitious.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Such as are not led away by an <hi>affected ſingularity</hi> in matters that are <hi>indiffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.16. with 18. Heb. 13.7, 17. Gal. 5.13. 2 Theſ. 3.6, 7. Rom. 16, 17, 18.</note> but do <hi>fix</hi> the uſe of their (otherwiſe) <hi>indeterminate</hi> Liberty, according to the <hi>commands of a juſt Authority,</hi> having reſpect to <hi>Polity, Decency, and good Order;</hi> they do govern themſelves prudently, according to <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> direction.</p>
            <p>But Laſtly, ſuch as out of an <hi>opinion of Religion</hi> do refuſe to conform to the Conſtitution of a juſt Authority, in <hi>determining</hi> the uſe of their <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Liberty about things <hi>indifferent,</hi> to the <hi>ends</hi> aforeſaid; <hi>they</hi> do walk<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>diſorderly</hi> in refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Government, and are (upon the matter) <hi>ſuperſtitious, ſchiſmatical, and ſcandalous.</hi> In ſhort then, according to the Apoſtles way of Arguing, <hi>[Touch not, taſte not, handle not]</hi> by a parity of reaſon, the bogling at <hi>thoſe</hi> Inſtances amongſt our ſelves appointed for Decency and Order, in the ſolemn performance of God's public Worſhip and Service, <hi>[viz. Touch not the Surplice, kneel not at the Sacrament, ſign not with the Croſs]</hi> are an <hi>Ataxy</hi> in Government, a denyal of Authority in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terming the uſe of things indifferent, a <hi>retrenchment</hi> of our Chriſtian Liberty, a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving</hi> of an <hi>old</hi> Superſtition in other Inſtances, and highly <hi>ſcandalous,</hi> by caſting a ſnare of <hi>neceſſity</hi> upon the Conſcience, and <hi>fixing</hi> an Opinion of <hi>Religion</hi> upon ſuch <hi>Abſtentions and Omiſſions,</hi> as are but <hi>indifferent</hi> in their own nature? This was charged upon <hi>diſſenting</hi> Brethren by a Learned Man in the time of Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">La Drios ubi ſupra pag. <hi>172.</hi>
               </note> where he faith thus, [<hi>Thoſe Miſtakers and Tolerators</hi> (ſo he calls them) <hi>have forgotten the laſt and extremeſt degree of Revolters, of Forſakers, of Refuſers and plain Contemners, whoſe caſe is much to be pitied, eſpecially of thoſe miſtakers, becauſe through them they</hi> (the reſt) <hi>are come into this downfall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this time I preſume you will readily conclude, that the Church hath great reaſon not to yield in thoſe things, which ſhe her ſelf calls <hi>indifferent,</hi> though the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> account them <hi>ſinful.</hi> For it is evident that hereby,</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:66526:5"/>
            <p n="1">1. She ſhould betray the Truth and our Chriſtian Liberty.</p>
            <p n="2">2. She ſhould give <hi>ſcandal</hi> to her <hi>weaker</hi> ſort of Children, who look upon theſe things as <hi>indifferent,</hi> and ſubmit to the <hi>uſe and practice</hi> of them as lawful, out of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Authority.</p>
            <p n="3">3. She ſhould hereby throw <hi>dirt</hi> upon the face of our firſt <hi>Reformers,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn their vigilant <hi>Succeſſors,</hi> not onely as <hi>unwiſe</hi> in putting theſe <hi>chips</hi> (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Irreverence of this Author) <hi>into our Porridge;</hi> but as <hi>unjuſt and tyrannous</hi> in impoſing things <hi>ſinful</hi> to wound the Conſcience.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, She ſhould hereby encourage theſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi> in their <hi>diſobedience,</hi> confirm them in their <hi>error and ſuperſtition,</hi> and ſo caſt a <hi>ſnare</hi> upon their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences. That ſhe may not be forced to do them <hi>this</hi> unkindneſs, the Church finds her ſelf obliged to deny them their <hi>unjuſt</hi> demands.</p>
            <p>I ſee in the opinion of this Author, <hi>theſe</hi> things are but <hi>bones of contention and ſtumbling blocks;</hi> but we know ſome Spirits are of that temper, they will <hi>ſtumble</hi> at the beſt Conſtitutions under Heaven, if themſelves have not a hand in them. Chriſt himſelf is ſuch a <hi>ſtumbling block,</hi> as cannot eſcape their wanton <hi>kicks and cenſures;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.8. Mat. 11.6.</note> which makes him leave this <hi>Aphoriſm</hi> upon record, <hi>Bleſſed is he whoſoever ſhall not be offended in me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us obtain ſo much Charity of theſe <hi>diſſenting</hi> Brethren, as to believe us in this our ſerious Profeſſion, that we look not upon the <hi>Rites and Ceremonies</hi> of the Church as <hi>matters</hi> of Religion, or <hi>parts</hi> of God's Worſhip; but as outward <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances</hi> of Decency and Order in the <hi>performance</hi> of it; and that coming into any other <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Church, which <hi>differs</hi> from us herein, we can as <hi>freely and ſincerely</hi> communicate with them as in our own.</p>
            <p>This Author tells us, <hi>Rome was not built in a day;</hi> but the ſtructure which takes up much time and pains in rearing up, may be <hi>pull'd down</hi> ſpeedily; and Children are able to demonſtrate this by their <hi>petty</hi> Experiments. The <hi>firſt</hi> Reformers (he confeſſes) caſt out <hi>abundance of filth and rubbiſh;</hi> and what ſhould be done more? I hope there are none ſo ill adviſed, as to overturn the <hi>Fabrick</hi> of the Church, and grub up her <hi>foundation.</hi> He ſays, <hi>they could not finiſh the work, nor add the top ſtone to the Reformation:</hi> but (I pray) what hindered them? did they want <hi>skill or wiſdom, zeal or courage, authority or power?</hi> I ſuppoſe there is no man ſo ſhameleſs as to affirm, <hi>they</hi> wanted any thing needful to an adviſable Reformation. He faith in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, <hi>ſuch was the iniquity of the Times, the rage of their Enemies, and the Oppoſition they met with, they could not do it.</hi> But reflecting upon the Proceedings of that Work, we find that none gave them <hi>more</hi> trouble from time to time than theſe <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting</hi> Brethren.</p>
            <p>To take offence at every thing which is in uſe and practice in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> (and for that very reaſon onely, Becauſe it is ſo) is very childiſh and ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous: and for this I appeal to all the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> with the moſt Learned and Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of the <hi>Reformed</hi> Churches. The Learned Author in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign,<note place="margin">La Deios, p. <hi>113.</hi>
               </note> ſo often mentioned, told <hi>thoſe</hi> Diſſenters of that Age, <hi>It is certain, that a great part of the publick prayers in that Book which the Romans uſe, was practiſed in the Church before the</hi> Beaſt <hi>came into that Chair: and oftentimes God's people have either taken or reſumed thoſe things to God's Worſhip, which have been abuſed by Idolatry. The ſpoils of</hi> Egypt <hi>and</hi> Jericho, <hi>the Veſſels of the Temple abuſed by the</hi> Babylonians, <hi>were again applied to God's Service. If we uſed any thing wherein the</hi> Pope <hi>ſheweth himſelf to be the</hi> Beaſt, <hi>as his worſhipping of dead Saints and Images, and the Maſs, and ſuch like; then we might be ſaid to bear his</hi> Image <hi>or his</hi> Mark; <hi>but in the Prayers that we have there is no part, no limb, no claw of that</hi> Beaſt.</p>
            <p>Some men (I know) to ſerve their own <hi>ends,</hi> and ſome for want of better <hi>infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> are apt to take up that old thredbare method, ſo fit to <hi>delude</hi> the hearts of the <hi>ſimple</hi> people. They are ready to charge others with an inclination to <hi>Popery,</hi> who ſtand at a further <hi>diſtance</hi> from it than themſelves, and upon much <hi>better</hi> grounds; not as raſh <hi>Zelots,</hi> but as prudent <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> not out of <hi>deſign to ſecure</hi> their Eſtates, but out of <hi>Conſcience to ſave</hi> their Souls.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:66526:6"/>
            <p>Yet we muſt not run ſo far from <hi>Rome</hi> (as the manner of ſome is) as to leave the Holy Scriptures, the Apoſtolical <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi> and the whole <hi>practice</hi> of the <hi>primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> Church, with our <hi>common Faith,</hi> the <hi>Creed</hi> and <hi>Sacraments</hi> behind us. The Lines that are drawn to the greateſt diſtance from this <hi>centre</hi> have the leaſt ſtrength in them.<note place="margin">L. Deios p. <hi>114</hi>
               </note> 'Tis very well ſaid of the Author even now commended, <hi>The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God muſt not faſhion themſelves like the</hi> Canaanites, <hi>nor the Heathen about them, in any thing wherein they are Idolatrous and Impious: but in that they have as men, God's people may be like them. As they are</hi> Papiſts <hi>we will not be like the</hi> Romans; <hi>but as they are</hi> Chriſtians, <hi>we may be like them. We muſt not uſe the</hi> Bible, <hi>nor the Name of</hi> God <hi>or</hi> Chriſt, <hi>nor</hi> Baptiſm <hi>if we will have nothing that they have.</hi> This was ſound <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Doctrine in the <hi>happy</hi> days of that <hi>Queen</hi> of ever <hi>bleſſed</hi> Memory.</p>
            <p>Conſonant hereunto the moſt <hi>eminent</hi> Proteſtant <hi>Divines,</hi> both <hi>at home</hi> and in <hi>forein</hi> Churches, do unanimouſly profeſs to <hi>deteſt and renounce</hi> nothing of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> but her Errors, her Corruptions, her Contagions, her Idolatry, Superſtition, and Tyranny. And albeit <hi>theſe her Pollutions</hi> would not permit them to <hi>communicate</hi> with her in the <hi>outward exerciſes</hi> of Religion (ſo <hi>contaminated;</hi>) yet they profeſs they never altered their <hi>purpoſe</hi> of perſevering in the <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> of thoſe things which are <hi>good in her.</hi> And for this I appeal to Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi> in his<note n="a" place="margin">Latin <hi>12.</hi> pag. <hi>88.</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Apology,</hi> and to Dr. <hi>Andrew Rivet</hi> in his<note n="b" place="margin">In Quarto, tom. <hi>1.</hi> tract. <hi>2.</hi> q. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>289.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cathol. Orthodoxus,</hi> and to the Learned <hi>H. Zanchy</hi> in his<note n="c" place="margin">Cap. <hi>24.</hi> ſect. <hi>19.</hi> in p. <hi>157.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Faith concerning matters of Religion,</hi> written when he was 70 years of age.</p>
            <p>Sir, when all is done, the onely <hi>Judges</hi> of publick Conſtitutions are our <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours,</hi> inveſted with Authority to that effect. And I muſt tell you freely, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver were matters more throughly <hi>ſifted</hi> and examined, for <hi>ſix ſcore</hi> years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, than theſe <hi>Church matters;</hi> never more care and pains taken, than to <hi>adapt</hi> and fit them to the <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lemnities</hi> of God's Worſhip.<note place="margin">See her Act for Uniformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty at the end</note> It was the care of Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> and her <hi>Commiſſioners,</hi> to ordain and publiſh ſuch <hi>Rites and Ceremonies,</hi> as were moſt for the <hi>advancement</hi> of God's glory, the <hi>edifying</hi> of his Church, and the <hi>due reverence</hi> of Chriſt's holy <hi>Myſteries and Sacraments.</hi> And truly I am of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that her <hi>Royal</hi> Highneſs and her <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> were <hi>as wiſe, as pious, and as learned</hi> as our <hi>Diſſenters.</hi> They cried out of things as <hi>Popiſh and Antichriſtian</hi> in <hi>thoſe</hi> days,<note place="margin">Pag. 154.</note> as <hi>theſe</hi> do in ours. And <hi>that</hi> Author ſo often mentioned did rarely encouter them at that time, and we need no other Confutation: <hi>Now then</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>how ſhall we know whetehr a thing be</hi> Popiſh and Antichriſtian <hi>or no? By the Names? That cannot be; Names of their</hi> (own) <hi>nature be</hi> indifferent: <hi>the Things contained in the Names as they are uſed of us might be examined. And how ſhall we find whether they be</hi> Popiſh and Antichriſtian? <hi>If they ſerve to promote</hi> Popery, <hi>then are they</hi> Popiſh, <hi>then are they</hi> Antichriſtian. <hi>But if none of theſe things</hi> (which they except againſt) <hi>help to maintain</hi> Idolatry, <hi>or the Pope's Supremacy, or mens Traditions againſt the written Word, or Free Will againſt the Grace of Chriſt, or mens Merits againſt Juſtification by Faith, or the Idol and Sacrifice of the Maſs, or Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimages, or Purgatory, or Prayer for the Dead, or Auricular Confeſſion,</hi> (whereby the Prieſt keeps the Lock and Key of the <hi>Penitent</hi>'s Conſcience, and makes it his <hi>Spy</hi> to diſcover his ſecret Inclinations, and the his <hi>Preſs-maſter</hi> to engage him to execute any deſign of miſchief) <hi>or Satisfactions for ſins by Penance, or Indulgences, or the keeping of the Word of God from the people in any unknown Tongue, or the like; if they do not maintain vice or unjuſtice, nor Hereſie amongſt us; but are directed to root out Popery, to keep us in the true faith, to advance the Word of God, to eſtabliſh our Juſtification by Faith, to further Repentance and good works, to puniſh ſin, to define that which is equal and right, to keep the common peace of the Church: Then are they not Popiſh, ſeeing they are bent and exerciſed to the ruin of Popery. But they are Chriſtian and holy, and appertaining to the Church of Chriſt, foraſmuch as they further the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Glory of Chriſt our Saviour.</hi> Thus ſtood the <hi>Church</hi> and the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion amongſt us in the day of Q. <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this moſt <hi>excellent</hi> Princeſs ſucceeded King <hi>James,</hi> a Prince <hi>wiſe and learned</hi> to a <hi>prodigy</hi> and wonder; and His <hi>Majeſty</hi> being importuned by the <hi>repeated</hi> noiſe and clamours of ſuch <hi>Diſſenters;</hi> was pleaſed <hi>himſelf</hi> to hear their Objections
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:66526:6"/>with an unwearied Patience, and (notwithſtanding the <hi>prejudice</hi> of his Education under <hi>Buchanan</hi>) he did ſolemnly declare, that all their <hi>exceptions</hi> were <hi>light and frivolous;</hi> for which reaſon he forthwith iſſued out his <hi>Royal Proclamation</hi> to rein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> which you may find well worth your reading about the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the former <hi>Book of Common Prayer.</hi> That <hi>wiſe and learned</hi> King (who was much more able to judge than you or I) look'd upon this our <hi>Engliſh Jeruſalem</hi> as a <hi>Bride</hi> made ready for her <hi>Husband;</hi> but theſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi> would be pulling off her <hi>dreſs</hi> and deflower her <hi>beauty,</hi> to ſhew their own skill in Religious <hi>Drapery</hi> and Trimming. And indeed they have made little leſs than <hi>Prophecy</hi> of the Words of that Perſon in the time of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> where he ſaith thus; [<hi>While men ſeek to perfect Churches, they will bring to paſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">L. Drios p. <hi>174</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that there will be amongſt us no Church at all.</hi>] If you would ſee the <hi>King of Saints</hi> in his <hi>beauty,</hi> (as that <hi>Anonymus</hi> hath it) you muſt have patience till you get your paſſage into Heaven; and if you would ſee <hi>Chriſt upon his throne,</hi> you muſt expect till he comes to ſit in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. When that great day of <hi>restitution</hi> comes, that <hi>corruption</hi> ſhall have put on <hi>incorruption,</hi> and <hi>infirmity</hi> be ſwallowed up of <hi>glory and perfection,</hi> then he will caſt <hi>all ſcandals</hi> out of his <hi>Kingdom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.27.</note> and preſent to himſelf <hi>a glorious Church not having ſpot or wrinkle,</hi> but completely holy and without <hi>blemiſh.</hi> In the mean while as long as the Church is <hi>militant,</hi> ſhe <hi>looketh forth as the morning, fair as the Moon, clear as the Sun;</hi> her Beauty is overcaſt with Clouds, ſtain'd with Spots, ſubject to Eclipſes. Chriſt hath told us, that <hi>Offences will come;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 6.10.</note> and the <hi>Tares will ſpring up amongſt the Wheat;</hi> and he that looks for any other <hi>Paradiſe or Heaven on Earth,</hi> does but feed upon his own <hi>dreams,</hi> and flatter himſelf with his own <hi>delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Name of God, what would men be at? Our pious and wiſe <hi>Reformers</hi> have ſo far departed from all the <hi>corruptions,</hi> from all the <hi>unwarrantable</hi> Doctrines and Practices of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that a <hi>Reverend</hi> Perſon well able to judge in the caſe, has put this his ſolemn Profeſſion into publick view;<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi>'s Sermon on 1 Cor. 3.15.</note> [<hi>I do believe in my conſcience the Church of</hi> England <hi>to be the beſt conſtituted Church this day in the world, and that as to the main the Doctrine, and Government, and Worſhip of it, are excellent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly framed to make men ſoberly religious, ſecuring men on the one hand from the wild freaks of</hi> Enthuſiaſm, <hi>and on the other from the follies of Superſtition.</hi>] And this I take the confidence to averr, that the grounds upon which the Church of <hi>England</hi> now ſtands gives us great <hi>advantage</hi> above <hi>all</hi> other particular Churches, to encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and beat off all the force of <hi>Rome.</hi> And <hi>this</hi> is undeniably evinced by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. It was the <hi>Obteſtation</hi> of that worthy Perſon in the time of Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">L Deios ubi ſupra <hi>106.</hi>
               </note> [<hi>All that is proper to</hi> Antichriſt <hi>we withſtand, and therefore</hi> Antichriſt <hi>ſeeing himſelf caſt off, and us not gathered in his Name, ſtriveth by force and policy to gather us to himſelf again.</hi>] For this reaſon it is, that thoſe Emiſſaries of his put themſelves into all <hi>ſhapes and trades,</hi> become <hi>Taylors</hi> and <hi>Shoomakers, Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Independ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, Anabaptiſts</hi> and <hi>Quakers,</hi> or men of the <hi>Fifth Monarchy,</hi> to attaque and ruin us. And as long as any <hi>Conventicles</hi> are allowed, there will be ſo many <hi>Scenes and Stages</hi> for Popiſh Prieſts and Jeſuits to act their parts <hi>undiſcernibly;</hi> and this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be avoided but by a <hi>ſtrict Conformity.</hi> Becauſe they are not able to ſtand againſt us in the <hi>open field</hi> by force of Argument, they attempt to do it by <hi>Stratagem,</hi> that is, <hi>by the moſt unjuſtifiable methods of Murthers, Treaſons, and Aſſaſſinations.</hi> If <hi>this</hi> Church of <hi>England</hi> were not the very <hi>beſt</hi> Church under Heaven, <hi>they</hi> would never impugn it with a Malice ſo implacable; and if they found it not much too <hi>hard</hi> for them, by the <hi>advantage</hi> of the ground it now ſtands on, they would never <hi>engage</hi> in ſuch <hi>deſperate</hi> courſes to remove it. Wherefore it highly concerns all worthy Perſons, who love the Settlement of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion here <hi>at home,</hi> (even in favour to the Proteſtants <hi>abroad</hi>) to <hi>unite</hi> their ſtrength and ſtudy by all juſt and prudent Methods to ſupport it; that our ſubtileſt Enemies the <hi>Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its</hi> may by no means obtain the advantage of an <hi>After game</hi> to ruin us. We know they are like <hi>Moles,</hi> and work <hi>under ground;</hi> if we ſuffer others to <hi>peck</hi> away any of our <hi>materials,</hi> which now ſtand ſo <hi>firm</hi> and ſo well <hi>cemented, they</hi> will inſinuate themſelves into a breach of a <hi>ſmall latitude</hi> to undermine our whole <hi>Fabric</hi> and enter in upon us <hi>poſtliminio.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:66526:7"/>
            <p>I confeſs, the <hi>union</hi> of all the Proteſtants as well <hi>abroad</hi> as <hi>at home,</hi> is a <hi>noble</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign; but whether it be <hi>practicable or needful,</hi> or whether we ſhall meet with a fair <hi>compliance</hi> from other Churches in ſuch an Attempt, is very doubtful. For, 1. That which pleaſeth the <hi>Lutherans</hi> will not pleaſe the <hi>Calviniſts;</hi> and to be ſure amongſt <hi>ſuch</hi> Proteſtants as are <hi>Subjects</hi> under <hi>Popiſh</hi> Dominions, this <hi>Project of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> is unpracticable. If we attempt to <hi>unite</hi> them to our ſelves, we betray them to be ruined by the <hi>jealouſie of their own</hi> Princes. Amongſt Proteſtants therefore under ſuch circumſtances no ſuch <hi>union</hi> can reaſonably be expected. 2. Nor is this at all <hi>needful,</hi> for do we not all profeſs it lawful for particular Churches to have their <hi>different Rites and Ceremonies, Forms and Cuſtoms?</hi> Do not all Proteſtant Churches declare, that it is their <hi>Chriſtian Liberty</hi> to have it ſo? and does not each particular Church and Party <hi>ſtifly</hi> adhere to their <hi>own</hi> Rites and Forms upon that account? and muſt we of the Church of <hi>England</hi> be the onely <hi>Changlings</hi> of the Reformation?<note place="margin">De Religione Fides cap. <hi>24.</hi> ſect. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> I pray let us conſider the Advice of the Learned <hi>Zanchy;</hi>
               <q>There are two ſorts of things (ſaith he) wherein the <hi>unity</hi> of the Church may conſiſt: The firſt, in ſuch things as are delivered in the Word of God; the other, in ſuch things as are not expreſſed in the Word, and of this ſort are many Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical <hi>Rites and Ceremonies.</hi> In the <hi>firſt</hi> kind we hold <hi>unity</hi> to be always and every where <hi>neceſſary:</hi> in the <hi>later,</hi> although <hi>unity</hi> is not of it ſelf <hi>neceſſary,</hi> but 'tis <hi>convenient</hi> to have <hi>different</hi> Rites, according to the <hi>conſtitution</hi> and quality of different Times and Places; nevertheleſs where <hi>a certain Order is appointed and received</hi> touching ſuch things, for the Edification of the Church; it is our Judgment, that there Unity in <hi>ſuch</hi> matters <hi>ought to be retained,</hi> and the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Church <hi>ought not to be diſturbed:</hi> according to the <hi>rule</hi> of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Let all things be done decently and in order, to the edification of the Church.</hi> Concerning which things we do wonderfully approve and embrace thoſe two Epiſtles of S. <hi>Auſtin, viz.</hi> 118. &amp; 119. to <hi>Januarius,</hi> after 70 years of age, when the heat of his <hi>Diſputes and Controverſial Labours</hi> were at an end.</q> This was the <hi>Faith and Religion</hi> which that Learned man <hi>profeſſed and died in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whatſoever <hi>alteration</hi> we can <hi>project,</hi> I am confident 'twill generally give more offence than ſatisfaction; and wiſe men in <hi>forein</hi> parts will be apt to <hi>value</hi> us the leſs for ſuch our <hi>levity.</hi> However with <hi>Free States and Princes</hi> which are <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> we may enjoy a firm <hi>union</hi> by a mutual <hi>confederation,</hi> (as is uſually done upon all other occaſions) without any <hi>change of Laws, Rites, Forms, or local Conſtitution</hi> on either part.</p>
            <p>And 3. will <hi>other ſorts of Proteſtants</hi> be ſo eaſily perſuaded to ſuffer their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate Conſtitutions to be diſputed and contradicted? Let us take our meaſures herein from our late <hi>Aſſembly of Divines,</hi> whoſe <hi>Advice and Reſolution</hi> to the then <hi>Parliament</hi> was this;<note place="margin">The Advice of the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith, ch. 20. ſect. 4.</note> 
               <hi>They who upon pretence of Chriſtian Liberty ſhall oppoſe any law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Power, or the lawful exerciſe of it, whether it be Civil or Eccleſiaſtical, reſiſt the Ordinance of God; and for their publiſhing ſuch Opinions, or maintaining of ſuch Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, as are contrary to the Light of Nature, or to the known Principles of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, whether concerning Faith, Worſhip, or Converſation, or to the Power of Godlineſs,</hi> (whereof we may be ſure they intended to be the Judges) <hi>or ſuch erroneous Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or Practices, as either in their own nature, or in the manner of publiſhing or main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining them, are deſtructive to the external peace and order, which Chriſt hath eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in the Church,</hi> (that is, by their Presbyterian Model) <hi>they may lawfully be call'd to account, and proceeded againſt by the Cenſures of the Church, and by the Power of the Civil Magiſtrate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let us leave the Proteſtants of <hi>forein</hi> Churches, and keep our eyes at <hi>home;</hi> and here we cannot but obſerve to our great grief, that the <hi>Sects and Factions are many and various,</hi> and which of them ſhould we deſign our kindneſs for? For <hi>Presbyterians or Independents, Anabaptiſts, Quakers, or Socinians?</hi> Where ever you reſolve to pitch, I believe you will have but a <hi>little</hi> to gratifie the humour of ſome <hi>Party,</hi> which you can never oblige. For it is not to be imagined, that our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours will ever part with <hi>ſo much</hi> as has been impetuouſly required; for then we ſhall lay a colourable ground to juſtifie their <hi>Solemn League and Covenant,</hi> with
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:66526:7"/>all thoſe <hi>horrid</hi> Miſchiefs which enſued upon it; and we ſhall moſt certainly <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form</hi> the Church, and <hi>unhinge</hi> the Government, which may be of a worſe conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence than a <hi>temporary</hi> Toleration. If you grant but <hi>little,</hi> they will conclude they have given the Church a <hi>defeat</hi> therein, and will <hi>triumph</hi> in it: yet this will be too <hi>weak</hi> a Charm to make them <hi>acquieſce,</hi> and be at peace with us. For this ſort of men (as well as others) are obſerved to be ſo reſtleſs in their humour, that inſtead of <hi>ſtudying to be quiet, and to do their own buſineſs,</hi> they are always labouring to be <hi>uppermoſt,</hi> and in order to <hi>that</hi> they are always ſtudying <hi>new</hi> Objections againſt all <hi>eſtabliſh'd Forms of Decency,</hi> maugre all <hi>alterations</hi> intended for their ſatisfaction. Sometimes they <hi>cry down</hi> the Rites and Ceremonies, becauſe they are <hi>dumb,</hi> that is, <hi>dark and unedifying:</hi> but ſince the <hi>dumb beaſt</hi> has had her mouth opened to convince the <hi>madneſs</hi> of theſe Prophets,<note place="margin">See the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face before the Common Prayer and Ceremonies, &amp;c.</note> they cry out againſt them for having too much Tongue, that is, for being <hi>too ſignificant and uſeful.</hi> And as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Inſtance of their Unquietneſs, we may obſerve their watchfulneſs and artifice in <hi>perverting</hi> ſuch charitable Diſcourſes, as are deſigned to draw them into the <hi>Communion</hi> of the Church, to <hi>palliate</hi> their Diſſent from it. And how <hi>tender and ſcrupulous</hi> ſoever they make themſelves at this day, yet they will not let us forget, that not very long ſince, while they ſtrained at the very ſame <hi>Gnats,</hi> they could ſwallow <hi>Camels;</hi> and thought it juſt to <hi>force</hi> others (as much as in them lay) to do the like.</p>
            <p>Sir, if theſe Practices have any affinity with the Definition of <hi>Infirmity,</hi> (or a <hi>weak</hi> Brother) I muſt confeſs my ſelf at a loſs to underſtand what it is to be <hi>ſtiff; wilful, and unteachable.</hi> In ſhort, by offering theſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi> to yield them <hi>they know not what,</hi> upon the Solicitation of <hi>we know not whom,</hi> we ſhall expoſe our ſelves and our Religion to no purpoſe. The <hi>Popiſh</hi> Party will upbraid us for our <hi>levity;</hi> and perhaps in departing from the <hi>decent</hi> and harmleſs Rites and Uſages of the <hi>Ancients,</hi> (long before <hi>Popery</hi> had a being) we may give a <hi>ſcandal</hi> to ſuch as have come over to us from <hi>their</hi> Communion. And what are we like to get by it? As far as I am able to diſcern, we ſhall give ground to a <hi>profeſs'd</hi> Adverſary, and make a wilful <hi>breach</hi> upon our wholſom <hi>Laws and Diſcipline,</hi> to make <hi>a new experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> For if it does not <hi>ſucceed</hi> well, (which none but God Almighty can fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee) how ſhall we <hi>recover</hi> our ground again? and who ſhall ſtand in the <hi>gap</hi> to make up the breach for us?</p>
            <p>We are come at laſt to the <hi>Authority</hi> alleaged by that <hi>Apocryphal Anonymus;</hi> in the firſt whereof I find a double miſtake, for firſt the Name of that Reverend Arch-Biſhop was not <hi>Edward</hi> but <hi>Edwin Sands,</hi> who died at <hi>York Aug.</hi> 8. 1588. The ſaid Reverend Perſon, when he was <hi>Vicechancellor of Cambridge,</hi> at the Inſtigation of the <hi>Duke of Northumberland,</hi> preached up the Title of <hi>Jane Grey,</hi> for which he was impriſoned by Queen <hi>Mary.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Godwyn</hi> of Biſhops.</note> Afterwards being ſet at liberty upon the Interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſome Friends, he went over into <hi>Germany,</hi> and ſtaid there till he was called back in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> From thence 'tis probable he might bring over with him ſome Inclinations to the <hi>Models of Reformation,</hi> which he had obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved amongſt ſome Proteſtants in thoſe Countries. But beſides this miſtake in the Name, there is a greater in the <hi>Title Page,</hi> and I am a little jealous it was <hi>wilful and adviſed;</hi> for he repreſents it as <hi>the ſentiment of the first Reformers,</hi> when it was but the <hi>ſingle Opinion</hi> of that Reverend Archbiſhop, in or about the thirtieth year of that <hi>Queens</hi> Reign; all the reſt of the Governours (as far as we are able to inform our ſelves) were of <hi>another</hi> Judgment, as their Succeſſors <hi>generally</hi> have been ever ſince. But let us hear the <hi>Biſtop</hi>'s own Words (at leaſt if they be his own) he ſaith thus; [<hi>I have ever been and preſently am perſuaded, that ſome of them</hi> (Rites and Ceremonies) <hi>be not ſo expedient for this Church now, but that in the Church Reformed, and in all this time of the Goſpel, wherein the Seed of the Scripture hath ſo long been ſown, they may better be diſuſed by little and little, than more and more urged.</hi>] This is that which the Archbiſhop declares, and it is obſervable, that he does not name any <hi>one</hi> of thoſe <hi>Rites and Ceremonies,</hi> but refers the <hi>particularities</hi> to the <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion of the Godly-wiſe.</hi> What have been <hi>diſuſed and altered</hi> ſince that time, I ſhall leave to the Obſervation of conſidering men: What are retain'd amongſt us, have
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:66526:8"/>been <hi>ſeverely and minutely</hi> examined; and the <hi>Godly-wiſe</hi> find them ſo far from a diſpoſition to choak the <hi>ſeed</hi> of the Goſpel, that they approve them as <hi>congenial</hi> to the general Dictates and Directions of it, and very <hi>decent</hi> in the <hi>ſolemn Worſhip and Service</hi> of God under it.</p>
            <p>That our <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Policy</hi> in ſome points may be <hi>better'd,</hi> that Biſhop does acknowledge, and ſo do we. In the Preface to the <hi>Commination</hi> we are told of a <hi>Godly Diſcipline in the Primitive Church,</hi> which both <hi>they and we</hi> wiſh heartily might be reſtored; but this is not to be hoped for, till the <hi>generality</hi> of men become more <hi>governable,</hi> that is, <hi>more humble, more obſequious,</hi> to wholeſom Diſcipline, and carry a greater <hi>veneration</hi> for the Authority of the Church.</p>
            <p>But that this Reverend Archbiſhop was not of the mind of theſe <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> his <hi>laſt Will and Teſtament,</hi> (which is here produced) gives us ſufficient Evidence. For he ſaith, 1. <hi>That the ſtate of a ſmall private Church</hi> (ſuch as <hi>Geneva</hi> for example) <hi>and the form of a large Chriſtian Kingdom, neither would long like, nor at all brook, one and the ſame Eccleſiaſtical Government.</hi> 2. He ſaith, <hi>Concerning Rites and Ceremonies by Political Conſtitutions authorized amongſt us, I am and have been perſuaded, that ſuch as are ſet down by public Authority in this Church of</hi> England, <hi>are no way either ungodly or unlawful, but may with a good Conſcience (for order and obedience ſake) be uſed of a good Chriſtian.</hi> Are the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> of this mind? why then do they not <hi>conform</hi> to them? and why does this their <hi>Advocate</hi> upbraid them as <hi>ſinful and ungodly,</hi> and charge them with an edge and ſting that <hi>wounds</hi> the Conſcience? 3. That Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Archbiſhop tells us further, <hi>I do utterly miſlike, even in my conſcience, all ſuch rude and undigeſted Platforms, as have been more lately and boldly, than either learned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or wiſely preferr'd; tending not to the Reformation, but to the deſtruction of the Church of</hi> England. What would this pious Soul have ſaid, if he had lived to ſee our <hi>tender conſciences</hi> cloathing themſelves in Arms of <hi>Steel,</hi> marching with <hi>Pikes, Swords, and Piſtols,</hi> bartering down our <hi>eſtabliſh'd</hi> Laws and <hi>Government</hi> with <hi>Guns</hi> and Cannons, and ſetting up their own <hi>new models,</hi> not with the noiſe of <hi>Axes and Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers,</hi> but with the more confuſed noiſe of Wars and Tumults, and with <hi>garments rolled in bloud?</hi> They have given this beſt of Churches the <hi>Stab,</hi> made the <hi>gaping wounds,</hi> yea and with their <hi>pretious balms</hi> have broken our much more <hi>precious head;</hi> and now they call earneſtly for a <hi>tender hand,</hi> for a <hi>cementing healing ſpirit,</hi> as if all the <hi>hurt</hi> had been done not <hi>by,</hi> but <hi>upon</hi> themſelves.</p>
            <p>Theſe Obſervations upon the Diſcourſe of that Reverend Perſon being ſubmitted to the Judgment of every Reader, I ſhall proceed to the remarkable paſſage of that Reverend and Worthy <hi>Dean,</hi> which he ſetteth down in theſe words; <hi>It is not for private perſons to undertake in matters of publick concernment; but I think we have no cauſe to doubt, but the Governours of our Church (notwithſtanding all the advantages of Authority, and we think of Reaſon too, on our ſide) are Perſons of that Piety and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that fox peace-ſake, and in order to a firm Union among Proteſtants, they would be content (if that would do it) not to inſiſt upon little things, but to yield them up, whether to the infirmity or importunity, or perhaps in ſome very few things, to the plauſible Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions of thoſe who differ from us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before I return an account of the Senſe of that <hi>Reverend and Learned</hi> Perſon, I ſhall endeavour to undeceive the nameleſs <hi>Allegator.</hi> He thinks that to ſome <hi>very few</hi> things, theſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi> have very <hi>plauſible Exceptions.</hi> Sir, I am heartily glad to hear their Exceptions are but <hi>plauſible,</hi> and reduced to ſo <hi>ſmall</hi> a number. We have <hi>Exceptions</hi> againſt the <hi>Presbyterian Diſcipline and Government,</hi> and againſt the <hi>Congregational Churches</hi> too, and thoſe not a <hi>few,</hi> and much more than plauſible. But what Conſtitution, what Court, what Perſon, what <hi>any thing</hi> in the world, ſhall be allowed to ſtand, if a <hi>few plauſible</hi> Exceptions be ſufficient to pull it down? There have been plauſible Exceptions againſt <hi>A Houſe of Lords,</hi> plauſible Exceptions againſt the <hi>beſt</hi> of Princes, and things that are moſt <hi>ſacred.</hi> When we hear of <hi>Exceptions and plauſible,</hi> we ſhould well conſider the Perſons to <hi>whom</hi> they are ſo: There are <hi>exceptions</hi> againſt the <hi>holy Scriptures;</hi> but they are <hi>plauſible<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> onely to the <hi>prophane Atheiſt;</hi> Exceptions againſt the <hi>eternal Son of God,</hi> but they are <hi>plauſible</hi> onely to <hi>Scribes, Phariſees, Hypocrites,</hi> to <hi>Jews, Infidels,</hi> and <hi>Hereticks.</hi> When <hi>Ignorance and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:66526:8"/>Faction</hi> have made exceptions, <hi>Pride and Intereſt</hi> will ſtrive hard to make them <hi>plauſible.</hi> A thing may be very <hi>plauſible</hi> which is no way <hi>juſt,</hi> but highly <hi>inconvenient.</hi> It is therefore an Argument of <hi>a light and ungenerous mind,</hi> to argue in matters of ſo great importance, from ſuch <hi>popular and looſe Topicks.</hi> Prudent and Pious Perſons were not wont of old to do ſo; we may inſtance in <hi>Hooker, Hammond, Sanderſon.</hi> Nor muſt we look upon this as the Judgment of that Reverend <hi>Dean,</hi> but as the fond Opinion which theſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi> have of their own Conceptions.</p>
            <p>Nor can this <hi>Allegator</hi> think, that <hi>a few things</hi> will ſatisfie them. To rectifie his Judgment herein, let him peruſe their <hi>Solemn League and Covenant,</hi> as the Mother of all the reſt, their <hi>Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory,</hi> their <hi>Form of Government for England and Ireland,</hi> their <hi>Confeſſion of Faith,</hi> their <hi>leſſer and larger Catechiſms,</hi> their <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> of the <hi>Presbyterian Government;</hi> and (ſince His Majeſty's hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Reſtruration) their <hi>Petition, with the Review and Alteration of the Book of Common Prayer;</hi> their <hi>Petition for Peace, with their Reformation of the Liturgy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, this confident <hi>Allegator</hi> looks at the wrong end of the <hi>Teleſcope,</hi> when he judges theſe matters to be ſo <hi>little.</hi> For to yield up ſuch things, and upon ſuch accounts as they demand them, we muſt yield up a branch of <hi>truth</hi> and our own <hi>reaſon,</hi> with ſome part of our <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> (which is never a whit the leſs conſiderable to us, becauſe we deſire not to make uſe of it for a cloke of Pride, Malice, or Diſobedience) Some <hi>Laws and Canons</hi> alſo are to be yielded up, and ſome rays of Authority to be eclipſed, if not extinguished, by this Conceſſion.</p>
            <p>Beſides, what is <hi>little</hi> in its <hi>own nature</hi> may be <hi>great</hi> in its conſequence. The <hi>Pin of a Watch</hi> is a ſmall matter if we look upon the <hi>bulk</hi> of it yet the loſs of ſuch a <hi>Pin</hi> diſorderss the whole <hi>Move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> or makes the Wheels to ſtand ſtill, and ſo you loſe your <hi>aim</hi> and the time or the day by it. The taking away of a little <hi>Turf</hi> is but a ſmall matter in appearance, but ſuch, as are well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the <hi>Po-Dyke Law,</hi> will tell you it may occaſion a breach in the whole <hi>bank,</hi> and let in ſuch an <hi>Inundation</hi> as may drown a fruitful <hi>Level:</hi> for which reaſon ſuch a wilful Breach is made <hi>Felony</hi> by Statute.</p>
            <p>But grant the things to be <hi>ſo little</hi> as is ordinarily imagined;<note place="margin">Deios ubi ſupra p. <hi>172.</hi>
               </note> for that Learned Man ſaid very right in the days of Queen <hi>Elizabeth, [The Controverſies wherein we differ have ſmall weight in the matters, and leſs in the proofs.</hi>] But it ſeems theſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi> have no great value for <hi>Authority,</hi> (when it was not <hi>veſted themſelves</hi>) that ſuch <hi>little</hi> matters can give them occaſion to quarrel with it. If the matters be <hi>ſmell,</hi> the performance is the more <hi>eaſie,</hi> and conſequently the diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience the more <hi>intolerable.</hi> And this is acknowledged by no leſs Authority than an <hi>Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament;</hi> for in the <hi>Preface</hi> to the Book of <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> under the Title of <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, that <hi>Although the keeping or omitting of a Ceremony, in it ſelf conſidered, is but a ſmall thing; yet the wilful and contemptuous tranſgreſſion and breaking of a Common Order and Diſcipline, is no ſmall offence before God.</hi> We find therefore that Inſtances of contempt in the <hi>ſmalleſt</hi> matters have been pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with the greater rigour. To pick up a few <hi>ſticks</hi> one would think no great violation of the <hi>Sabbath;</hi> yet 'twas ſo high an <hi>affront</hi> to Government, the <hi>Lawgiver</hi> would not diſpenſe with it.<note place="margin">Num. 15<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 32.</note>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true, ſuch Affronts may be prevented, if the Law be changed by the <hi>ſame</hi> Authority that made it; but this courſe in preventing <hi>one,</hi> would draw on <hi>another,</hi> and a much <hi>greater</hi> miſchief. For as that Reverend <hi>Dean</hi> obſerves, [There is no greater diſparagement to a man's underſtanding,<note place="margin">Dr <hi>Tilloiſon</hi>'s <hi>Sermon on</hi> 1 Cor. 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>no greater argument of a light and ungenerous mind, than raſhly to charge ones Religion.] Eft enim proprium viri nobilie conſtantem eſſe in re laudabili honoréque digna; nec ſinere ſe ab honeſto propoſito vel ſecundis vel adverſis rebus abduci,</hi> ſaith the Learned <hi>Zanchy. This chopping and changing</hi> leaves a legible brand of <hi>unſteddineſs and levity,</hi> and argues want of <hi>good adviſement,</hi> when the Law was <hi>firſt</hi> eſtabliſhed: and this is the readieſt way to make the graveſt Councils <hi>ridiculous,</hi> and their Laws <hi>contemptible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This that <hi>wiſe and learned</hi> Prince very well underſtood,<note place="margin">K. JAMES.</note> and therefore in his Proclamation for the Uniformity of Common Prayer he concludes thus: <q>And laſt of all we do admonish all men, that hereafter they ſhall not expect nor attempt any further Alteration in the Common and Publick Form of God's Service, from this which is now eſtabliſhed;<note place="margin">This Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was printed before the old Book of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer.</note> for that neither will we give way for any to preſume, that our own Judgment having determined in a matter of this weight, ſhall be ſwayd to alteration by the frivolous ſuggeſtion of any light ſpirit. Neither are we igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the Inconveniences that do ariſe in Government, by admitting Innovation in things once ſettled by mature deliberation; and how neceſſary it is to uſe Conſtancy in the upholding of the publick Determinations of States: for that ſuch is the unquietneſs and unſtedfaſtneſs of ſome Diſpoſitions, affecting every year new Forms of things, as if they ſhould be followed in their Unconſtancy, would make all Actions of State ridiculous and contemptible; whereas the ſtedfaſt maintaining of things by good advice eſtabliſhed, is the Weal of all Commonwealths.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And now <hi>(Sir)</hi> I ſhall take leave to do right to that <hi>Reverend</hi> and Worthy <hi>Dean,</hi> whoſe Words are alleaged by this <hi>Apocryphal</hi> Writer to his own ends, but with a Conſtruction far diſtant from the <hi>Dean</hi>'s intended ſence and meaning.</p>
            <p>For 1. The <hi>Dean</hi> does avouch himſelf to be of our <hi>Governours</hi> ſide, but theſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi> are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly againſt them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Dean</hi> tells you, <hi>It is not for private perſons to undertake in matters of publick concernment:</hi> but whatever they have done ſince, I am ſure the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> in the time of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> thought it lawful to attempt any thing (which they were pleaſed to call a <hi>Reformation</hi>) by Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, Tumult, and Violence; and ſometimes they did act accordingly <hi>without and againſt</hi> Authority.</p>
            <p>In evidence whereof we need produce no other than the words of that <hi>Author</hi> ſo often men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Laur. Deios</hi> in the ſaid Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe p. 163, 164.</note> 
               <q>This their Liberty (ſaith he of thoſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi>) is one of the chief Points wherein they ſtand. Here neither Prince, nor Counſellour, nor Biſhop, nor Law muſt reſtrain them from refuſing or caſting off whatſoever they miſlike; or from taking upon them, and putting
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:66526:9"/>in practice any thing they have determined or concluded to be done; ſeeing according to their conceit they have ſound out, that Biſhops and all other Officers in our Church are Popiſh, and that the Miniſtery (as they ſuppoſe) beareth Popiſh Names and Marks, and the Laws are Popiſh; they will neither ſue to Prince nor Council for the removing of any of theſe things; but with all ſpeed caſt the Yoke from their own necks. And ſeeing they have found in their fancies, that an Elderſhip, and no other Laws but the written Word is to be heard, therefore they will erect theſe things amongſt themſelves.</q> And it were to be wiſhed that the <hi>ſame</hi> hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour did not reign <hi>incorrigibly</hi> among them at this day; witneſs the late Practices in <hi>Scotland,</hi> which agree exactly with their <hi>ſeditious</hi> Principles, for which Ireſer the <hi>Reader</hi> to a Book entituled <hi>Raviliac Redivivus,</hi> and their late <hi>Declaration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The pious Inclination of that Reverend <hi>Dean</hi> was for a <hi>not-inſiſting upon a few little things.</hi> Theſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi> are for a change of <hi>all, viz.</hi> the <hi>Liturgy, Diſcipline, and Government</hi> of the Church.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Theſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi> demand a change of things as <hi>ſinful.</hi> The <hi>Dean</hi> taken them onely for <hi>indifferent,</hi> having all the <hi>advantages of Authority and Reaſon;</hi> which he would never have alleaged if he had thought ſuch things <hi>ſinful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The <hi>Dean</hi> doubts not in the laſt of the <hi>Piety and Prudence</hi> of the <hi>Governours</hi> of the Church; but he finds no ſuch <hi>relenting melting</hi> temper in theſe <hi>Diſſenters.</hi> For after ſuch a <hi>Condeſcention</hi> in our Governours (as he ſuppoſes to be attainable) he is ſtill doubtful of thoſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi> Conformity and Obedience, which makes him ſay, <hi>[If that would do it.]</hi> In ſhort, when his heart was <hi>warm</hi> with Meditation and a Diſcourſe of Charity, the Reverend <hi>Dean</hi> freely utters his pious Sentiments for <hi>peace-ſake,</hi> and in order to a firm <hi>union among Proteſtants, [If that would do it.]</hi> And what Chriſtian Soul would not do the like for an End ſo noble and glorious? This was no more in effect than what fell from the mouth of that <hi>Great and Excellent</hi> Perſon the Lord Archbiſhop <hi>Juxton,</hi> who diſcourſing with my ſelf about <hi>Indulgence to Diſſenters,</hi> (at his firſt coming to <hi>Lambeth</hi> after the King's Return) was pleaſed thus to expreſs himſelf: <q>That if the yielding of ſome few ſmall matters would win them to joyn cordially with us in the Practice of the reſt, he could very well be content with it.</q> And this ſignified juſt as much as Mr. <hi>Dean</hi>'s Expreſſion with this Proviſo, <hi>[If that would do it.]</hi> But I muſt not diſſemble, that His <hi>Grace</hi> added thus much; <q>You know Mr. <hi>N.</hi> I have ſometimes ſate at the <hi>Helm,</hi> and truly I have ſtudied the temper of theſe men, and could never find them ſo<note n="*" place="margin">The Biſhop added, That there was no way to govern this ſort of people, but by a streight Rain.</note> ingenuous. For gratifie them in any thing, and you do but encourage them to ask more. They will uſe your Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcention as an Argument of your Conviction, that your own Practice is ill, and their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries juſt and reaſonable. Nor will they reſt ſatisfied, till all matters of Decency and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der be laid aſide, to make way for their own new-fangled Innovations.</q> If my <hi>Lord</hi> were miſtaken in the temper of theſe <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> I ſhall be heartily glad to ſee it in their <hi>practice and compliance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the interim it concerns the Prudence of all that are in Authority, to have regard to thoſe <hi>Worthies</hi> who have ſate at the <hi>Stern</hi> heretofore, who without all doubt watch'd all opportunities to ſecure the <hi>Government,</hi> with the Intereſt of the Church and Kingdom. To call their Prudence and Piety into queſtion, will make our own ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and put our Integrity under ſome diſpute. Such were <hi>Cranmer, Whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gift, Bancroft,</hi> (to name no more) amongſt our Biſhops; and amongſt our <hi>Sovereign Princes</hi> ſuch were Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> K. <hi>James,</hi> and K. <hi>Charles,</hi> of over bleſſed me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory. To ſecure the <hi>Ark</hi> of God, and keep it <hi>ſteddy,</hi> they could never be induced to ſet it upon <hi>new Carriages,</hi> nor to truſt the <hi>ſtumbling</hi> Oxen with the <hi>conduct</hi> of it, but left that to the care of the <hi>ancient Hierarchy.</hi> We ſee <hi>(Sir)</hi> the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of <hi>thoſe</hi> great perſons is precious and had in <hi>honour;</hi> and if we conſult our own <hi>reputation</hi> with our <hi>tranquillity,</hi> we ſhall find it the faireſt and neareſt way to it, to tread in their ſteps. And if theſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi> (notwithſtanding their <hi>pretences</hi> to Religion) ſhould be of <hi>implacable ſpirits, reſolved to carry then beats and animoſities down to the grave with them, their ſpeedy march off would be a mercy to the Church and Nation, unleſs God pleaſe to mollifie their hearts into a dutiful compliance,</hi> upon terms of Truth, Juſtice, and Ingenuity. And if this their zealous <hi>Advocate</hi> be not able to prevail with them to this effect, we may very well expect from his modeſty, that he ſhould acquieſce in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes, or at lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that he ſhould ſolicit their Cauſe no more, till he hath given us ſome tolerable ſatisfaction to theſe important <hi>Quare's.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. What <hi>ſort of Diſſenters</hi> he does plead for?</item>
               <item>2. What <hi>Commiſſion</hi> he can ſhew that they have appointed him to be their <hi>Advocate?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. What <hi>Alterations</hi> they are which he can undertake <hi>they</hi> ſhall acquieſce in?</item>
               <item>4. What <hi>Security</hi> he can give the Church, that they will <hi>cordially</hi> joyn with us in the <hi>practice</hi> of all the reſt?</item>
               <item>5. What he can propound to ſatisfie <hi>Diſſenters</hi> of <hi>other</hi> ſorts, who may plead an equal right to the like<note n="*" place="margin">See Puritans-Papiſmus pag. <hi>29.</hi> by Oliver Ormerod, Printed <hi>1605.</hi>
                  </note> Indulgence.</item>
            </list>
            <p>But I perceive this is too hard a task for him; whereupon he does very wiſely excuſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from it in theſe words, [<hi>It is not for me, the meaneſt of ten thouſand, to act the</hi> Dictator; <hi>no, no, I will turn</hi> Orator, <hi>and humbly pray.</hi> When his Prayer is done, I muſt remind this <hi>Orator</hi> of his own Acknowledgments; <q>That Peace is that Legacy which our deareſt Lord hath leſt to his Diſciples. That Union and Communion among Chriſtians is both the beauty and ſtrength of the Church. That which renders her lovely as a City compacted together, and terrible as an Army with Banners.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Next, I muſt remin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him of that Reverend <hi>Dean</hi>'s Doctrine; <q>That men ought to bring along with them a peaceable diſpoſition, and a mind ready to comply with the Church in which they were born and baptized, in all reaſonable and lawful<note n="*" place="margin">The Archbiſhop owns ours to be lawful. See above.</note> things, and deſirous upon any terms that are tolerable to return to the Communion of it; a mind free from paſſion and prejudice, from peeviſh Exceptions and groundleſs and endleſs ſcruples.</q> Herein the nameleſs <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> proſeſſeth moſt cheerfully to yield to him: <q>Oh that it may be according to his word, that (as he ſays) there may be no more crumbling into Parties and Factions, but that all the ſons and daughters of <hi>Zion</hi> may worſhip God in the beauty of holineſs, with one ſhoulder and with one conſent,</q> (<hi>of mind and mouth, in forms and geſtures,</hi> And then (our Morals and Converſation being conſonant to our Religious Worſhip) we may aſſure our ſelves, that upon all our <hi>Aſſemblies</hi> there will be a <hi>glory,</hi> and upon that Glory a <hi>defence</hi> and through God's bleſſing that Defence will be <hi>Impregnable:</hi> Which God of his mercy grant us. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
